This image illustrates the interconnected networks that make up the Internet. It begins with a Mobile Network: a cell phone tower surrounded by a car receiving Internet through its antenna, a stoplight, multiple smartphones, and a laptop. The cell phone tower connects to a router; this router connects to a National or Global ISP, illustrated by a group of routers. This network connects to a Local or Regional ISP, represented by a group of routers. These routers send signals through telephone lines to a Home Network and an Enterprise Network. The Home Network includes a router and a base station sending signals to a laptop computer, a refrigerator, a thermostat, a desktop computer and a wireless keyboard. The Enterprise Network includes several routers and link-layer switches sending signals to desktop computers and servers, and a base station sending wireless signals to laptops and a tablet device. Below this is the key, identifying the various devices included above.

In this graph, the x-axis, labeled "N," begins at 0 and moves rightward in increments of five to 35. The y-axis, labeled "Minimum distribution time," begins at 0 and moves upward in increments of .5 to 3.5. The client-server architecture is represented by a series of plotted points that appear as blue dots and which are connected with a blue line. The P2P architecture is represented by a series of plotted points that appear as black squares and which are connected with a black line.

Both client-server and P2P begin at 0 on the x- and y-axes. The client-server line rises steadily as it moves rightward along the x-axis at nearly a 90-degree angle. At 5 on the x-axis it reaches 0.5 on the y-axis; at 10 on the x-axis it reaches 1.0 on the y-axis; at 15 on the x-axis it reaches 1.5 on the y-axis; this pattern continues until the line ends at 35 on the x-axis and 3.5 on the y-axis.

The P2P line rises more modestly and levels out quickly. At 10 on the x-axis it reaches 0.5 on the y-axis; at 25 on the x-axis it reaches the mid-point between 0.5 and 1.0 on the y-axis; and at 35 on the x-axis it has risen only incrementally higher.

In this illustration, a black arrow extends diagonally downward from left to right and points to a blue circle labeled "Wait for call 0 from above." A blue arrow extends from the top of this circle and arcs rightward to a second blue circle. The arrow has two labels separated by a horizontal line. On top: "rdt_send (data)."

On bottom: "sndpkt=make_pkt (0, data, checksum) udt_send (sndpkt)."

The second blue circle is labeled "Wait for ACK or NAK 0." A smaller blue arrow extends from the upper right side of this circle and travels in a clockwise motion to the bottom right side of the same circle. This arrow has two labels. On top: "rdt_rcv (rcvpkt) &&(corrupt (rcvpkt) | |isNAK (rcvpkt))."

On bottom: "udt_send (sndpkt)."

A blue arrow extends from the lower right side of this circle and arcs downward to the upper right side of a third blue circle. This arrow has two labels. On top: "rdt_rcv (rcvpkt) && notcorrupt (rcvpkt)&& is ACK (rcvpkt)."

On bottom: capital lambda.

The third blue circle is labeled "Wait for call 1 from above." A blue arrow extends from the bottom of this circle and arcs leftward to a fourth blue circle. This arrow has two labels. On top: "rdt_send (data)."

On bottom: "sndpkt=make_pkt (1, data, checksum) udt_send (sndpkt)."

The fourth blue circle is labeled "Wait for ACK or NAK 1." A smaller blue circle extends from the lower left side of the circle and travels in a clockwise motion to the upper right side of the same circle. This arrow has two labels. On top: "rdt_rcv (rcvpkt) && (corrupt (rcvpkt) | |isNAK (rcvpkt))."

On bottom: "udt_send (sndpkt)."

A blue arrow extends from the upper left side of the fourth arrow and arcs upward to the first blue circle. This arrow has two labels. On top: "rdt_rcv (rcvpkt) && notcorrupt (rcvpkt) && is ACK (rcvpkt)."

On bottom: capital lambda.

In this illustration, a black arrow extends diagonally downward from left to right and points to a blue circle labeled "Wait for 0 from below." A blue arrow extends from the top of this circle and arcs rightward to a second blue circle. The arrow has two labels separated by a horizontal line. On top: "rdt_rcv(rcvpkt)&& notcorrupt(rcvpkt) && has_seq0(rcvpkt)." On bottom:

"extract(rcvpkt,data) deliver_data(data) sndpkt=make_pkt(ACK,checksum) udt_send(sndpkt)."

The second blue circle is labeled "Wait for 1 from below." A smaller blue arrow extends from the center right side of the circle and arcs sharply back toward the upper right side of the same circle. This arrow has two labels. On top: "rdt_rcv(rcvpkt) && corrupt(rcvpkt)." On bottom: "sndpkt=make_pkt(NAK,checksum) udt_send(sndpkt)."

A smaller blue arrow also extends from the center right side of the circle and arcs sharply back to the lower right side of the same circle. This arrow has two labels. On top: "rdt_rcv(rcvpkt)&& notcorrupt (rcvpkt)&&has_seq0(rcvpkt)."

On bottom: "sndpkt=make_pkt(ACK,checksum) udt_send(sndpkt)."

A blue arrow extends from the bottom of the second blue circle and arcs leftward to the bottom of the first blue circle. This arrow has two labels. On top: "rdt_rcv(rcvpkt) && notcorrupt(rcvpkt) && has_seq1(rcvpkt)."

On bottom: "extract(rcvpkt,data) deliver_data(data) sndpkt=make_pkt(ACK,checksum) udt_send(sndpkt)."

A smaller blue arrow extends from the center left side of the first blue circle and arcs sharply back to the bottom left side of the same circle. This arrow has two labels. On top: "rdt_rcv(rcvpkt)&& notcorrupt (rcvpkt)&&has_seq1(rcvpkt)."

On bottom: "sndpkt=make_pkt(ACK,checksum) udt_send(sndpkt)."

A smaller blue arrow extends from the center left side of the first blue circle and arcs sharply back to the top left side of the same circle. This arrow has two labels. On top: "rdt_rcv(rcvpkt)?&& corrupt(rcvpkt)."

On bottom: "sndpkt=make_pkt(NAK,checksum) udt_send(sndpkt)."

In this illustration, a black arrow extends diagonally downward from left to right and points to a blue circle labeled "Wait for call 0 from above." A blue arrow extends from the top of this circle and arcs rightward to a second blue circle. The arrow has two labels separated by a horizontal line. On top: "rdt_send(data)."

On bottom: "sndpkt=make_pkt(0,data,checksum) udt_send(sndpkt)."

The second blue circle is labeled "Wait for ACK 0." A smaller blue circle extends from the top right side of the circle and travels in a clockwise motion to the center right side of the same circle. This arrow has two labels. On top: "rdt_rcv(rcvpkt) && (corrupt(rcvpkt)|| isACK(rcvpkt,1))."

On bottom: "udt_send(sndpkt)."

A blue arrow extends from the bottom right side of the second circle and arcs downward to a third circle. This arrow has two labels. On top: "rdt_rcv(rcvpkt)? && notcorrupt(rcvpkt) && isACK(rcvpkt,0)."

On bottom: capital lambda.

A blue arrow extends from the bottom of the third circle and arcs leftward to a fourth blue circle. This arrow has two labels. On top: "rdt_send(data)."

On bottom: "sndpkt=make_pkt(1,data,checksum) udt_send(sndpkt)."

The fourth blue circle is labeled "Wait for ACK 1." A smaller blue arrow extends from the lower left side of the circle and travels in a clockwise motion to the center right side of the same circle. This arrow has two labels. On top: "rdt_rcv(rcvpkt) && (corrupt(rcvpkt)|| isACK(rcvpkt,0))."

On bottom: "udt_send(sndpkt)."

A blue arrow extends from the upper left side of the fourth circle and arcs upward to the first blue circle. This arrow has two labels. On top: "rdt_rcv(rcvpkt)? && notcorrupt(rcvpkt) && isACK(rcvpkt,1)."

On bottom: capital lambda.

In this illustration, a black arrow extends diagonally downward from left to right and points to a blue circle labeled "Wait for 0 from below." A blue arrow extends from the top of this circle and arcs rightward to a second blue circle. The arrow has two labels separated by a horizontal line. On top: "rdt_rcv(rcvpkt) && notcorrupt(rcvpkt) && has_seq0(rcvpkt)."

On bottom: "extract(rcvpkt,data) deliver_data(data) sndpkt=make_pkt(ACK,0,checksum) udt_send(sndpkt)."

The second blue circle is labeled "Wait for 1 from below." A smaller blue circle extends from the top right side of the circle and travels in a clockwise motion to the center right side of the same circle. This arrow has two labels. On top: "rdt_rcv(rcvpkt) && (corrupt(rcvpkt)|| has_seq0(rcvpkt))."

On bottom: "sndpkt=make_pkt(ACK,0,checksum) udt_send(sndpkt)."

A blue arrow extends from the bottom of the second circle and arcs leftward back to the first blue circle. This arrow has two labels. On top: "rdt_rcv(rcvpkt) && notcorrupt(rcvpkt) && has_seq1(rcvpkt)."

On bottom: "extract(rcvpkt,data) deliver_data(data) sndpkt=make_pkt(ACK,1,checksum) udt_send(sndpkt)."

A smaller blue arrow extends from the bottom left side of the first blue circle and travels in a clockwise motion to the top left side of the same circle. This arrow has two labels. On top: "rdt_rcv(rcvpkt) && (corrupt(rcvpkt)|| has_seq1(rcvpkt))."

On bottom: "sndpkt=make_pkt(ACK,1,checksum) udt_send(sndpkt)."

In this illustration, a black arrow extends diagonally downward from left to right and points to a blue circle labeled "Wait for call 0 from above." A blue arrow extends from the top of this circle and arcs rightward to a second blue circle. The arrow has two labels separated by a horizontal line. On top: "rdt_send(data)."

On bottom: "sndpkt=make_pkt(0,data,checksum) udt_send(sndpkt) start_timer."

The second blue circle is labeled "Wait for ACK 0." A smaller blue circle extends from the top right side of the circle and arcs sharply back to the center right side of the same circle. This arrow has two labels. On top: "rdt_rcv(rcvpkt) && (corrupt(rcvpkt)|| isACK(rcvpkt,1))."

On bottom: capital lambda.

A second smaller arrow extends from the center right side of the circle and arcs sharply back to the lower right side of the same circle. This arrow has two labels. On top: "timeout."

On bottom: "udt_send(sndpkt) start_timer."

A blue arrow extends from the bottom of the second circle and arcs downward to a third circle. This arrow has two labels. On top: "rdt_rcv(rcvpkt)? && notcorrupt(rcvpkt) && isACK(rcvpkt,0)."

On bottom: "stop_timer."

The third circle is labeled "Wait for call 1 from above." A smaller blue arrow extends from the center right side of the circle and arcs sharply back to the bottom right side of the same circle. This arrow has two labels. On top: "rdt_rcv(rcvpkt)."

On bottom: capital lambda.

A blue arrow extends from the bottom of the third circle and arcs leftward to a fourth blue circle. This arrow has two labels. On top: "rdt_send(data)."

On bottom: "sndpkt=make_pkt(1,data,checksum) udt_send(sndpkt) start_timer."

The fourth circle is labeled "Wait for ACK 1." A smaller blue arrow extends from the bottom left side of this circle and arcs sharply back to the center left side of the same circle. This arrow has two labels. On top: "rdt_rcv(rcvpkt) && (corrupt(rcvpkt)|| isACK(rcvpkt,0))."

On bottom: capital lambda.

A second smaller blue arrow extends from the center left side of the fourth circle and arcs sharply back to the top left side of the same circle. This arrow has two labels. On top: "timeout."

On bottom: "udt_send(sndpkt) start_timer."

A blue arrow extends from the top of the fourth circle and arcs upward back to the first circle. This arrow has two labels. On top: "rdt_rcv(rcvpkt) ?&& notcorrupt(rcvpkt) && isACK(rcvpkt,1)."

On bottom: "stop_timer."

A smaller blue circle extends from the center left side of the first circle and arcs sharply back to the top left side of the same circle. This arrow has two labels. On top: "rdt_rcv(rcvpkt)."

On bottom: capital lambda.

In this illustration, a black arrow extends diagonally downward from left to right and points to a blue circle labeled "Wait." The black arrow itself is labeled with a capital Lambda over: "base=1 nextseqnum=1."

A blue arrow extends from the top left side of the circle and arcs to the top right side of the circle. This arrow contains two labels, separated by a horizontal line between them. The top label reads: "rdt_send(data)."

The bottom reads: "if(nextseqnum<base+N){ sndpkt[nextseqnum]=make_pkt(nextseqnum,data,checksum) udt_send(sndpkt[nextseqnum]) ?if(base==nextseqnum) start_timer nextseqnum++ } else refuse_data(data)."

A blue arrow also extends from the bottom right side of the circle and arcs upwards to the top right side of the circle. This arrow has two labels. On top: "timeout."

On bottom: "start_timer udt_send(sndpkt[base]) udt_send(sndpkt[base+1]) ... udt_send(sndpkt[nextseqnum-1])."

A blue arrow also extends from the bottom left side of the circle and arcs rightward to the bottom right side of the circle. This arrow has two labels. On top: "rdt_rcv(rcvpkt) && notcorrupt(rcvpkt)."

On bottom: "base=getacknum(rcvpkt)+1 If(base==nextseqnum) stop_timer else start_timer."

A blue arrow also extends from the center left side of the circle and arcs downward to the bottom left side of the circle. This arrow has two labels. The top: "rdt_rcv(rcvpkt) && corrupt(rcvpkt)."

The bottom: capital lambda.

This illustration uses a familiar structure of a sender and receiver positioned side-by-side, with dotted lines extending vertically downwards from each to indicate the respective timelines and send and receive operations depicted with blue arrows going back and forth between the two timelines. Here we see multiple operations, as five packets are being sent by the sender. However, this illustration also includes sequence numbers for each operation; each sequence runs from 0 to 9, though different groups of numbers are highlighted in blue in each step of each operation.

Operations begin at the topmost part of the sender's timeline, at a point labeled "pkt0 sent." Sequence numbers 0123 are highlighted. A blue arrow extends diagonally downward to the right towards the receiver's timeline, to a point labeled "pkt0 rcvd, delivered, ACK0 sent." Sequence numbers 1234 are highlighted. Below pkt0 on the sender's timeline, pkt1 is sent. Sequence numbers 0123 are highlighted. An arrow extends to the receiver's timeline, to a point labeled "pkt1 rcvd, delivered, ACK1 sent." Sequence numbers 2345 are highlighted. Below pkt1 on the sender's timeline, pkt2 is sent. Sequence numbers 0123 are highlighted. An arrow extends halfway and stops, indicating a loss. Below this point on the sender's timeline, pkt 3 is sent from a point labeled "pkt3 sent, window full." Sequence numbers 0123 are highlighted. An arrow extends to the receiver's timeline to a point labeled "pkt3 rcvd, buffered, ACK3 sent." Sequence numbers 2345 are highlighted.

Below pkt3 on the sender's timeline, the sender receives ACK0, sent by the receiver in response to pkt0. This point on the sender's timeline is labeled "ACK0 rcvd, pkt4 sent." Sequence numbers 1234 are highlighted. An arrow extends to the receiver's timeline to a point labeled "pkt4 rcvd, buffered, ACK4 sent." Sequence numbers 2345 are highlighted. ACK4 is sent.

Below pkt4 on the sender's timeline, the sender receives ACK1, sent by the receiver in response to pkt1. This point on the sender's timeline is labeled "ACK1 rcvd, pkt5 sent." Sequence numbers 2345 are highlighted. An arrow extends to the receiver's timeline to a point labeled "pkt5 rcvd; buffered, ACK5 sent." Sequence numbers 2345 are highlighted. ACK5 is sent.

Below pkt5 on the sender's timeline, pkt2 experiences TIMEOUT. This point on the timeline is linked to the previous point on the timeline where pkt2 was originally sent. Pkt2 is now resent. Sequence numbers 2345 are highlighted. An arrow extends to the receiver's timeline to a point labeled "pkt2 rcvd, pkt2,pkt3,pkt4,pkt5 delivered, ACK2 sent." Sequence numbers 6789 are highlighted. ACK2 is sent.

The final point on the sender's timeline is labeled "ACK3 rcvd, nothing sent." Sequence numbers 2345 are highlighted.

This illustration uses a familiar structure of a sender-here labeled "Sender window (after receipt)"-and receiver-here labeled "Receiver window (after receipt)"-positioned side-by-side, with dotted lines extending vertically downwards from each to indicate the respective timelines and send and receive operations depicted with blue arrows going back and forth between the two timelines. However, in this version an angled gray rectangle appears between the sender and receiver, representing a curtain that prevents one from being able to see the actions taken by the other. This illustration also incorporates sequence numbers for every step of each operation; each sequence appears as 0123012, and different groups of numbers are highlighted in blue for each step.

Operations begin at the topmost portion of the sender's timeline, where a blue arrow extends horizontally from left to right, passes through the curtain, and intersects with the receiver's timeline. The arrow is labeled "pkt0." The number sequence 012 is highlighted in blue. In response to pkt0, the receiver sends ACK0, represented by a blue arrow that extends diagonally downward to the left, passes through the curtain, and terminates in an X. Sequence numbers 123 is highlighted. Beneath pkt0 on the sender's timeline, we see pkt1, also represented by a horizontal arrow and also including the number sequence 012. In response to pkt1, the receiver sends ACK1, which also passes through the curtain and then terminates. Number sequence 230 is highlighted. Below pkt1 on the sender's timeline, we see pkt2, also represented by a horizontal arrow and also including the number sequence 012. In response to pkt2, the receiver sends ACK2, which also passes through the curtain and then terminates. Number sequence 301 is highlighted.

Further down the sender's timeline, we arrive at a point labeled "timeout, retransmit pkt0." The number sequence 012 is highlighted. An arrow extends horizontally to the receiver's timeline, to a point labeled "receive packet with seq number 0."

In this illustration, estimated RTT and sample RTT are graphed in order to show their differences.

The x-axis, labeled "Time (seconds)," begins at 1 and moves in increments of seven to 106. The y-axis, labeled "RTT (milliseconds)," begins at 100 and moves upwards in increments of fifty to 350. Estimated RTT is represented by a black line, while Sample RTT is represented by a blue line.

Estimated RTT and Sample RTT begin at the same point on the graph: at 1 on the x-axis and just under 200 on the y-axis. The black line rises relatively smoothly, reaching just over 200 on the y-axis at about 22 on the x-axis, before leveling out and extending rightward with little fluctuation. By 71 on the x-axis, Estimated RTT has reached just below 250 on the y-axis. There are small dips and bumps before ending at about 225 on the y-axis when we reach 106 on the x-axis.

By contrast, Sample RTT extends rightward in a series of sharp rises and drops. By 15 on the x-axis, Sample RTT has spiked above 250 on the y-axis, then drops to 200, then rises to 225, then drops below 200, etc. It continues this pattern of spikes and drops as it progresses. By 71 on the x-axis it begins spiking dramatically, hitting 300, then dropping below 200, then hitting 325 and dropping, 350 and dropping, etc. It ends just below 200 on the y-axis when we reach 106 on the x-axis.

In this illustration, Host A is represented by a desktop computer while Host B is represented by a server. Their interaction begins at the topmost portion of Host A's timeline, where a blue arrow, labeled "seq=92, 8 bytes of data," extends diagonally downward to the right to Host B's timeline. This point on Host B's timeline is labeled "ack=100." A blue arrow extends from this point diagonally downward and left back to Host A's timeline. Below Host A's first transmission is a second, labeled "seq=100, 20 bytes of data." This one extends rightward and terminates, indicating a loss. Below this, Host A sends a third transmission, labeled "seq=120, 15 bytes of data." This one extends rightward and intersects with Host B's timeline, at a point labeled "ack=100." A blue arrow extends from this point diagonally downward and left back to Host A's timeline. Below Host A's third transmission is a fourth, labeled "seq=135, 6 bytes of data." This one extends rightward and intersects with Host B's timeline at a point labeled "ack=100." A blue arrow extends from this point diagonally downward and left back to Host A's timeline. Below Host A's fourth transmission is a fifth, labeled "seq=141, 16 bytes of data." This one extends rightward and intersects with Host B's timeline at a point labeled "ack=100." A blue arrow extends from this point diagonally downward and left back to Host A's timeline. Host A responds to this transmission by sending a final one, labeled "seq=100, 20 bytes of data."

The area on Host A's timeline between the receipt of Host B's first response and the end of the represented timeline is labeled "Timeout." However, Host A is able to retransmit the terminated submission before the timeout expires.

In this illustration we see Host A and Host B side-by-side, with A on the left and B on the right. Each host appears next to its protocol stack. Between and below them is a cloud representing the network; inside the network is a series of five routers. Each router has two blue arrows passing through it, representing pathways of data.

Host A is sending data to Host B. This data originates in the top layer of Host A's protocol stack; it travels down through the stack and into one of the routers in the network. The data passes through the first router and into a second, through this router and into a third, and through this router and upwards into Host B's protocol stack. The data arrives in the top layer of Host B's protocol stack.

A gray arrow, representing a message of congestion information, extends from the second router to the second-to-top layer of Host A's protocol stack. This arrow is labeled "Direct network feedback." A second gray arrow extends from the second-to-top layer in Host B's protocol stack to the same point in Host A's protocol stack. This arrow is labeled "Network feedback via receiver."

In this illustration we see a desktop computer labeled Host A, and a server labeled Host B positioned side-by-side. Each host has a dotted line extending vertically downward, representing the passage of time. A series of blue arrows extending from one side to the other represents the steps of communication in a TCP connection.

The connection begins at the topmost point on Host A's timeline. A blue arrow extends diagonally downward to the right to Host B's timeline. This arrow is labeled "one segment." A blue arrow extends from this point on Host B's timeline diagonally downward to Host A's timeline. The area on Host A's timeline between the two arrows is labeled as "RTT." At this point on Host A's timeline, two arrows extend diagonally downward to Host B's timeline. These are labeled "two segments." Two arrows extend from Host B's timeline back to Host A's timeline. In response, four arrows extend from Host A to Host B. These are labeled "four segments." In response, four arrows extend from Host B back to Host A.

This illustration is presented as a graph. The x-axis is labeled "Transmission round;" it begins at 0 and moves in increments of one to 15. The y-axis, labeled "Congestion window (in segments)," begins at 0 and moves in increments to two to 16. A dashed line, labeled "ssthresh," begins at 0 on the x-axis and 8 on the y-axis and moves horizontally to the right. At 8 on the x-axis, the dashed line shifts to 6 on the y-axis, and moves horizontally along the x-axis to 15.

TCP Tahoe is represented by a series of plotted points in blue along the graph. The first appears at 1 on the x-axis and about 1 on the y-axis, before moving to 2 on the x- and y-axes, then 3 on the x-axis and 4 on the y-axis. From there it jumps to 4 on the x-axis and 8 on the y-axis, hitting the threshold. From there it moves diagonally upward until it hits 12 on the y-axis at 8 on the x-axis, and then falls sharply to 1 on the y-axis at 9 on the x-axis. From there it climbs to 6 on the y-axis at 12 on the x-axis before ending just under 10 on the y-axis and 15 on the x-axis.

TCP Reno is represented by a series of plotted points in black. The first appears at 9 on the x- and y-axes. They move steadily upwards and to the right at a 45-degree angle, ending at 15 on the x- and y-axes.

This illustration uses the image first introduced in figure 1.1 and repeated in subsequent chapters, of the interconnected networks that make up the Internet. These networks include a mobile network, a national or global ISP, a local or regional ISP, a home network, and an enterprise network. Each network includes at least one router, though the ISPs and the enterprise network include several. Each router shown here is also associated with a protocol stack; end system H1 and end system H2 have five-layer protocol stacks, while all other protocol stacks have three layers. In all of the three-layer protocol stacks, the top layer is highlighted in blue.

In this image, a laptop computer in the home network is designated as "End system H1." End system H1 is associated with a five-layer protocol stack-from top to bottom, the layers are labeled as follows: Application, Transport, Network, Data link, Physical. End system H1's protocol stack is highlighted in blue at the "Network" layer. The router in the home network is designated as "Router R1," and its three-layer protocol stack is labeled, from top to bottom, as follows: Network, Data link, Physical. The "Network" layer is highlighted in blue. Two of the routers in the Local or Regional ISP are associated with protocol stacks, and both are highlighted in blue at the "Network" layer. Two of the routers in the enterprise network are associated with protocol stacks, and both are highlighted in blue at the "Network" layer. A server in the enterprise network is designated as "End system H2." End system H2 is associated with a five-layer protocol stack and, as with end system H1, the "Network" layer is highlighted in blue.

In this illustration we see three rows of input and output ports, separated by a large box labeled "Switch fabric." Data packets in the third box of each input port are queued to be transferred. In the top row, we see two dark blue packets, both destined for upper output port. In the middle row we see one gray packet, destined for the lower output port. And in the bottom row we see two packets, one dark blue-destined for the upper output port-and one light blue-destined for the middle output port. A label at the top of this figure explains: "Output port contention at time t-one dark packet can be transferred." Arrows indicate the destined path for each packet.

A second version of this illustrate appears below, showing the result of HOL blocking. One dark blue packet has been transferred from the upper input port to the upper output port, leaving one dark blue packet remaining in the upper input port. The light blue and dark blue packets remain in the lower input port, and the gray packet has been transferred to the lower output port. A label at the top of this figure explains: "Light blue packet experiences HOL blocking."

In this illustration, we see multiple organizations connecting to two different ISPs, and those ISPs sending data to the Internet. The ISPs appear as clouds and are positioned one on top and one below. The top ISP is labeled "Fly-By-Night ISP. To the left of this ISP are a series of organizations positioned in a vertical line. The top organization is designated Organization 0 and assigned the IP address 200.23.16.0/23. The next organization is designated Organization 1 and assigned the IP address 200.23.18.0/23. The next organization is designated Organization 2 and assigned the IP address 200.23.20.0/23. A series of other organizations is implied, and the last organization is designated Organization 7 and assigned the IP address 200.23.30.0/23. All of these organizations connect to the Fly-By-Night ISP, which connects to a large cloud on the right, representing the Internet. The connection is labeled "Send me anything with addresses beginning 200.23.16.0/20."

Below this we see a second ISP, labeled "ISPs-R-Us." A series of implied organizations connect to this ISP, and the ISP connects to the Internet. This connection is labeled "Send me anything with addresses beginning 199.31.0.0/16."

This illustration depicts a series of interactions between a router network and an SDN controller in order to illustrate a link state change. The interactions are numbered to correspond with the numbered list on page 417.

The interaction begins with the network of routers, which appears at the bottom of the illustration. There are four routers arranged in a diamond shape: the left point of the diamond is r1, the top of the diamond is r2, the bottom of the diamond is r3, and the right point of the diamond is r4. An arrow, labeled 1 and indicating step one of the interaction, points from r1 to the box labeled "OpenFLow" in the lowest layer of the SDN controller. The arrow, now labeled 2, continues from OpenFlow to a box labeled "Link state info" in the middle layer of the SDN controller-this is step two. The arrow, now labeled 3, goes past a box labeled "statistics" in the middle layer and into a box labeled "Dijkstra's link-state routing" in the top layer of the SDN controller. A second arrow, labeled 4, points back and forth from link-state info to Dijkstra's link-state routing. The arrow, now labeled 5, points downward from Dijkstra's link-state routing and into a box labeled "flow tables" in the middle layer of the SDN controller. The arrow travels through the bottom layer and through the OpenFlow, and emerges-now labeled 6. The arrow splits into three arrows, pointing to r1, r2, and r4.

In this illustration, we see the horizontal axis at the top of the figure, labeled "Space." A, B, C, and D are plotted along the axis at equal intervals. On either side of the horizontal axis are two dotted lines extending vertically downward, both labeled "Time." About an eighth of the way down the left-hand timeline is a plotted point labeled t0. At this point, B begins its transmission. The transmission appears as a thick dark blue band in the shape of an upside-down letter V. The transmission begins at the point of the V and extends diagonally downwards in both directions.

At a slightly lower point than t0 on the left-hand timeline is a plotted point on the right-hand timeline labeled t1. At this point, D begins its transmission, which also appears as a thick band in the shape of an upside-down letter V, however this one is light blue rather than dark blue. The transmission begins at the point of the V and extends diagonally downward in both directions. Quickly, the two bands overlap and the space of their overlap appears as light and dark blue stripes. Most of the figure appears in this striped pattern.

At the center of this figure is a link-layer switch with six connections extending from all sides. Connection 1 extends diagonally downward to the left into a second link-layer switch. The line between them is identified as "100 Mbps (fiber)." This second link-layer switch connects to a network of computers labeled "Electrical Engineering."

Connection 2 extends vertically downward into a third link-layer switch. The line is similarly identified as 100 Mbps (fiber), and the switch similarly connects to a network of computers, this one labeled "Computer Science." The lines between the switch and the computers are identified as "Mixture of 10 Mbps, 100 Mbps, 1 Gbps, Cat 5 cable."

Connection 3 extends diagonally downward to the right and into a fourth link-layer switch. The line between them is similarly identified as 100 Mbps (fiber), and this switch similarly connects to a network of computers, this one labeled "Computer Engineering."

Connection 4 extends horizontally to the right and into a server. The line between them is identified as "1 Gbps," and the server is labeled "Mail server."

Connection 5 extends diagonally upward to the right and into a second server. The line between them is 1 Gbps and the server is labeled "Web server."

Connection 6 extends diagonally upward to the left and into a router. The line is identified as "1 Gbps." A second line extends from the router horizontally to the left and to the external Internet.

In this illustration, we see three separate networks-a school network, Comcast's network, and Google's network-and the interactions between them required in a simple web page request.

The school's network is on the left side of the figure, and has been assigned the IP address 68.80.2.0/24. Comcast's network is to the right of the school network, and has been assigned the IP address of 68.80.0.0/13. Google's network is below Comcast's network, and has been assigned the IP address 64.233.160.0/19.

The interaction begins with Bob's laptop in the school network, which has been assigned the MAC address of 00:16:D3:23:68:8A and an IP address of 68.85.2.101. A blue arrow labeled "1-7" (corresponding to steps 1-7 on pages 501-2) extends back and forth from Bob's computer to a link-layer switch and then beyond the switch to a router within the school's network. The port on the router is assigned the MAC address 00:22:6B:45:1F:1B.

A new arrow, labeled 8-13, extends back and forth from Bob's computer, through the switch, and back to the router.

A third arrow, labeled 14-17, extends back and forth from Bob's computer, through the switch, through the router and into a router in Comcast's network. The arrow extends to a second router, which is connected to a server labeled "comcast.net DNS server," and which has been assigned the IP address 68.87.71.226.

A fourth arrow, labeled 18-24, extends back and forth from Bob's computer, through the switch, through the router in the school's network, through a router in Comcast's network, into a second router in the Comcast network, and into Google's network. The arrow goes through one router, through a second, and into a server labeled "www.googl.com" Web server," and which has been assigned the IP address 64.233.169.105.

This illustration uses a graph format to show the characteristics of selected wireless network standards. The x-axis represents coverage area; from left to right, it includes: Indoor, 10-30m; Outdoor, 50-200m; Mid range outdoor, 200m-4Km; and Long range outdoor, 5Km-20Km. The y-axis represents link rate; from bottom to top it includes: 384 Kbps, 1 Mbps, 4 Mbps, 5-11 Mbps, 54 Mbps, 450 Mbps, and 1300 Mbps.

At "Indoor" on the x-axis, we see the following networks: none at 384 Kbps, 802.15.1 at 1 Mbps, none at 4 Mbps, 802.11b at 5-11 Mbps, 802.11a,g at 54 Mbps, 802.11n at 450 Mbps, and 802.11ac at 1300 Mbps.

4G: LTE stretches from 5-11 Mbps to 450 Mbps on the y-axis and from Outdoor to Long range outdoor on the x-axis. 802.11a,g point-to-point stretches from 5-11 Mbps to 54 Mbps on the y-axis and from Outdoor to Long range outdoor on the x-axis. Enhanced 3G: HSPA stretches from 4 Mbps to 5-11 Mbps on the y-axis and from Outdoor to Long range outdoor on the x-axis. 3G: UMTS/WCDMA, CDMA2000 is at 384 Kbps on the y-axis and stretches from Outdoor to the middle of Long range outdoor on the x-axis. 2G: IS-95, CDMA, GSM sits below 384 Kbps on the y-axis and stretches from Outdoor to Long range outdoor on the x-axis.

This figure uses two illustrations to depict active and passive scanning. The image on the left depicts passive scanning. In this illustration we see two basic service sets, labeled "BSS 1" and "BSS 2," that overlap to form a common area in between them. BSS 1 includes a cell tower labeled AP1, and BSS2 includes a cell tower labeled "BSS 2." In the center common area is a laptop computer labeled H1. A blue arrow points from AP1 to H1 and a second arrow points from AP 2 to H1. Both arrows are labeled 1 and correspond to a numbered sequence below the figure. 1 = "Beacon frames sent from APs." An arrow labeled 2 points from H1 back to AP 2. 2 = "Association Request frame sent: H1 to selected AP." A blue arrow labeled 3 points from AP2 to H1. 3 = "Association Response frame sent: Selected AP to H1."

The second figure, depicting active scanning, is the same as the first. In this figure, however, a blue line labeled 1 rises from H1 and extends in either direction towards AP1 and AP2. 1 = "Probe Request frame broadcast from H1." Blue arrows labeled 2 point from AP1 to H1 and from AP2 to H1. 2 = "Probes Response frame sent from APs." A blue arrow labeled 3 points from H1 to AP2. 3 = "Association Request frame sent: H1 to selected AP." A blue arrow labeled 4 points from AP2 to H1. 4 = Association Response frame sent: Selected AP to H1."

This figure depicts a Bluetooth piconet as a large blue circle with smaller circles contained within it. A key identifies the three different types of smaller circles: dark blue circle labeled "M" = Master device, light blue circle labeled "S" = Slave device, and gray circle labeled "P" = Parked device. At the center of the piconet is a master device; arrows point from either side of it like hands on a clock pointing at 3 and 9. These arrows indicate the radius of coverage. Above the arrows are two parked devices and one slave device-one parked device sits near the edge of the radius at the 2 o'clock point, while the other is nearer the master device and above it to the left. The slave device sits about halfway between M and the edge of the circle's radius, at the 10 o'clock point.

Below the arrows are two slave devices and two parked devices. One slave device sits near the 8 o'clock point while the other sits between the M and the radius edge at 5 o'clock. One parked device sits halfway between M and the radius edge just to the left of 6 o'clock, while the other parked device sits nearer the edge at 4 o'clock.

In this illustration, we see the same BSS from the previous figure, connected this time to a series of switches. Above the BSS is a dotted line; area above the line is indicated as "Control plane" while area below the line is "Data plane."

Within the BSS is a small device, labeled "UE" and operating in the control plane. Each base transceiver station is connected to a single network controller, labeled "eNodeB" and operating in the control plane. The eNodeB is connected to a network of routers operating in the data plane and arranged in a square. The top left router is connected to a network controller labeled "MME," operating in the control plane. The top right router is connected to a network controller labeled "HHS," operating in the control plane. The bottom right router is connected to a network controller labeled "S-GW" and another labeled "P-GW," both operating in the control plane. All of the devices operating in the control plane are connected one to the next by a dotted line.

This figure once again uses the illustration from the previous figures of the home and visited networks. Here, however, the visited network has been replaced by a "Foreign network being visited at session start." This network includes a router, labeled "Anchor foreign agent," a link-layer switch, and the mobile node, which has been grayed out. A new network, labeled "New foreign network," has been added adjacent to the foreign network being visited at session start. This new network includes a router, labeled "New foreign agent," a link-layer switch, and a mobile node.

A blue arrow, labeled 1 and corresponding to numbered steps given in the text on page 571, extends from the Corresponding Agent to the Foreign Anchor Agent. A thicker blue arrow labeled 2 extends from the grayed-out mobile node in the foreign network being visited at session start to the mobile node in the new foreign network. A blue line labeled 3 points back and forth between the New Foreign Agent and the Mobile Node in the new foreign network. A blue line labeled 4 points back and forth between the Anchor Foreign Agent and the New Foreign Agent. And a blue line labeled 5 extends from the Anchor Foreign Agent to the Mobile Node in the new foreign network.

In this illustration, we see a telephone at top right that is labeled "Correspondent." At top left we see a blue cloud representing the home network, which includes the outline of a house containing a mobile switching center (MSC). Below the correspondent, we see a blue cloud representing the public switched telephone network (labeled "PSTN"). To the left of the PSTN we see the outline of a house containing a mobile switching center (MSC). This is labeled "Anchor MSC." A second house and MSC is below the PSTN, and a third is just outside of it to the bottom right. Each of the three MSCs not in the home network connects to a series of cellular coverage areas and base transceiver stations. A mobile user, depicted as a car, appears next to the second cellular coverage area.

A blue arrow extends from the Correspondent through the PSTN and into the MSC in the home network. A blue arrow extends from there through the PSTN and into the Anchor MSC. A blue arrow extends from the Anchor MSC and into the Mobile User via the MSC in the second cellular coverage area.

This figure uses a series of labeled and shaded boxes to illustrate message authentication.

At the left, we see a light blue box labeled "m," representing the Message. Below this we see a freestanding "s," representing the Shared Secret. Blue arrows extend down from the message and up from the secret and point to the right to a white box labeled "H(.)." A blue arrow extends from this box to the right, to a dark blue box identified as "H(m+s)," then points upwards to a white circle containing a plus sign. A blue arrow also points from the original message to this circle. A blue arrow extends rightward from the white circle and to a cloud representing the Internet. Above this arrow is the light blue box labeled m with a dark blue box attached to it. The blue arrow points rightward from the Internet and splits; one end, containing the original message, points upwards and then rightwards at a white box labeled "H(.)." The freestanding s also appears here and a blue label extends from it to the white box as well. A blue arrow containing the dark blue box labeled "H(m+s)" points rightward from the white box and then downward to a light blue diamond shape, labeled "Compare." The other end of the blue arrow, containing the dark blue box, points downward and then to the right and then upwards to the light blue diamond.

In this illustration we see Bob on the left looking rightward and Alice on the right looking leftward. A dotted arrow extends vertically from each, representing the passage of time. A blue arrow labeled "TCP SYN" extends diagonally downward to the right from Bob's timeline to Alice's timeline. Her response, labeled "TCP/SYNACK," extends diagonally downward to the right to Bob's timeline. This transaction is labeled "(a)," corresponding to the steps given in the text on page 635. Bob's response, labeled "TCP ACK," extends from Bob to Alice.

Below this point on Bob's timeline a new blue arrow, labeled "SSL hello," extends diagonally downward from Bob to Alice. Her response, labeled "certificate," extends from Alice to Bob. This transaction is labeled "(b)." There is a small gap on Bob's timeline, labeled "(c), Create Master Secret (MS)," followed by a blue arrow labeled "EMS = K A+ (MS)" that extends from Bob to Alice. This point on Alice's timeline is labeled "Decrypts EMS with KA- to get MS."

In this illustration, we see again data organized into four different layers with a cloud between the second and third layers. In this figure, the layers are (from top to bottom): Original stream, Interleaved stream, Received stream, and Reconstructed stream.

In the original stream we see four units of data, which appear as long rectangles that have been divided into small four small segments. The first unit of data (from left to right) contains four segments labeled 1, 2, 3, and 4. The next contains 5, 6, 7, and 8, the next contains 9, 10, 11, and 12, and the last contains 13, 14, 15, and 16. Each of the first segments in each unit-1, 5, 9, and 13-is highlighted in blue.

In the interleaved stream, the data has been reorganized so that the first unit of data includes the highlighted segments from above: 1, 5, 9, and 13. The next unit has been similarly reorganized to include the second segments of each unit from the original stream, and includes 2, 6, 10, and 14. The next includes 3, 7, 11, and 15, and the last includes 4, 8, 12, and 16. Arrows connect the segments from the original stream to their counterparts in the interleaved stream.

Dashed arrows extend downward from the units in the interleaved stream, through the cloud, and to the same units now residing in the received stream. The third unit-including 3, 7, 11, and 15-now appears as a loss.

In the reconstructed stream, the units appear as they had in the original stream, except that the four segments that were lost are now missing.

In this illustration we see a series of servers and clients arranged in a pyramid. At the top of the pyramid is a server labeled "SIP registrar upenn.edu." Below and to the left is a server labeled "SIP proxy umass.edu," and below to the right is a server labeled "SIP registrar eurcom.fr." Below these to the left is a computer labeled "SIP client 217.123.56.89," and below to the right is a computer labeled "SIP client 197.87.54.21."

A black arrow, labeled 1 and corresponding to a series of steps given in the text starting on page 710, extends upwards from SIP client 217 to SIP proxy umass.edu. An arrow labeled 2 extends from SIP proxy umass.edu to SIP registrar upenn.edu. An arrow labeled 3 extends from the same registrar back to the previous SIP proxy. An arrow labeled 4 extends horizontally rightward from SIP proxy umass.edu to SIP registrar eurcom.fr. An arrow labeled 5 extends downward from this SIP registrar to SIP client 197. An arrow labeled 6 extends back from this client to the previous registrar. An arrow labeled 7 extends leftward from SIP registrar eurcom.fr to SIP proxy umass.edu. An arrow labeled 8 extends downward from this SIP proxy to SIP client 217. And a blue arrow labeled 9 extends horizontally back and forth between the two SIP clients.

In this illustration we see two simplified versions of the leaky bucket policer process depicted in the previous figure: flow 1 is on top and flow 2 is below it. We see simplified versions of the bucket, the tokens, the token wait area, and the token remove area. In flow 1, the dropping token is labeled r1 and the bucket is labeled b1. To the right of the token remove area is the WFQ area, which is shown here as a rectangle divided vertically into eight segments-the first four segments are white and the last four segments are blue. The WFQ connects on the right to a large unlabeled circle, and the connection extends from the circle to the right side of the figure.

The bottom flow is the same, except that the dropping token is labeled rn and the bucket is labeled bn. The WFQ also has four white segments and four blue segments, and also connects to the large with circle. Flow 1's connection from WFQ to the circle includes a point labeled W1, while Flow 2's connection includes a point labeled Wn. A blue arrow extends from W1 to Wn and then curves back around in a circular motion to W1 again.

In this illustration, we see a series of hosts and routers-there are eight hosts and seven total routers, and each router is numbered. Routers 1, 3, 5 and 6 form a square with R1 at top left, R3 at bottom left, R5 at bottom right, and R6 at top right. Each of these routers connects to the next. R2 is to the left of the square and connects with R1 and R3. R4 is below the square and connects with R3 and R5. R7 is to the right of the square and connects to R5. R1, R2, R6, and R7 all connect to two hosts, one shaded gray and one shaded blue. The blue host connected to R1 is labeled "H1." The blue host connected to R2 is labeled "H2." The blue host connected R6 is labeled "H4." The blue host connected R7 is labeled H3. R1, R2, R6, and R7 are all shaded light blue, while R3, R4, and R5 are dark blue. A key at the bottom of the figure identifies R2 as a leaf router and R3 as a core router. A light blue arrow points from H1 to R1, to R3. A light blue arrow points from H2 to R2 to R3. A dark blue arrow points from R3 to R4 to R5. A light blue arrow points from R5 to R6 to H4. And a light blue arrow points from R5 to R7 to H3.

In this illustration, we see a desktop computer at top left shaded in blue connected to a series of routers by a line that slopes diagonally downward to the right. There are four routers, all shaded blue. The first router also connects to a computer, shaded gray. The second router connects to a router on the left, shaded gray, which connects to two computers, also shaded gray. This second router also connects to a router on the right, shaded gray. These two gray routers connect with the third blue router as well. The fourth router connects to two computers, one gray and one blue. A blue arrow, labeled "QoS call signaling setup," begins in the top left computer and travels down the slope through each of the blue routers. As it passes each router, we see smaller blue arrows pointing from the arrow to the router and from the router to the arrow, and these are labeled "Request/reply." The blue arrow passes through all four blue routers and into the blue computer connected to the fourth blue router.